Margaret Cruikshank papers, 1971-1986 LSC.1847
UCLA Library Special Collections
Margaret Cruikshank papers
1971-1986
UCLA Library Special Collections
Cruikshank, Margaret
LSC.1847
6.5 Linear Feet (13 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize box)
The Margaret Cruikshank Papers consist of drafts, background/research notes, correspondence and publicity materials for three published works edited by Cruikshank: Lesbian Path (1980, 1982, 1985), a collection of autobiographical writings; Lesbian Studies (1982), a women's history and lesbian studies text and New Lesbian Writing (1984), a lesbian literature anthology. The Cruikshank papers also consist of background/research files for women's studies and lesbian studies courses taught by Cruikshank and related correspondence and publicity materials. Personal correspondence is also included in the collection.
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
NOTE: Series 7: Cruikshank Personal Correspondence (1971-1976) is open for reading by lesbians only.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Margaret Cruikshank, 1997.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 6411103
Biography
A longtime lesbian activist and distinguished academic, Margaret Cruikshank (b. 1940) began her work in the 1970s at a time when lesbian studies barely existed and was one of the few lesbian academics in the U.S. to identify herself professionally as a lesbian. Her work has centered on raising awareness of lesbians within the academic profession and addressing the exclusion of lesbian literature and criticism from traditional canons and women's studies.
A native of northern Minnesota, Cruikshank came out as a lesbian in the Minneapolis lesbian-feminist community in the mid-1970s. She lived in the Midwest until 1977, when she moved to San Francisco. During the 1970s, Cruikshank played an active role in the explosion of lesbian feminist politics and culture and she began publishing on lesbian topics in 1975. Writing under her own name as well as various pseudonyms, Cruikshank has written numerous essays, articles and reviews that have appeared in a wide variety of periodicals including Gay Community News, Motheroot Journal, The Radical Teacher, Focus, Journal of Homosexuality and The Advocate.
With a Ph.D. in Victorian literature from Loyola University in Chicago, IL, Cruikshank began teaching English in 1969 at various colleges and universities in the Midwest. In 1975, she began teaching at Mankato State University (now called Minnesota State University, Mankato), which at that time, did not have a women's studies program. Cruikshank helped establish the first women's studies department at Mankato State University, for which she served as director between 1975 and 1977. Her experience arriving at Mankato State University in 1975 as a closeted academic and leaving the university in 1977 as an open lesbian in a university setting began a life-long commitment to increasing the visibility and solidarity of lesbians within the academic profession.
In 1977, Cruikshank moved to San Francisco where she worked as a resources director for a short-lived grassroots project, the Gay National Educational Switchboard, which provided a toll-free information line. In August 1980, Cruikshank became head of a small program in Continuing Education at the University of San Francisco (USF). Five months after she was hired at USF she was fired. Subsequently, Cruikshank taught in the English department at City College of San Francisco (CCSF) where she taught English as a Second Language (ESL) and worked with other CCSF faculty and administrators to incorporate lesbian and gay studies into the curriculum. These efforts resulted in the organization of CCSF's Castro/Valencia Campus and, in 1982, the appointment of Cruikshank as the first woman to teach CCSF's gay and lesbian literature course. Cruikshank taught an introductory women's studies course and lesbian and gay literature at CCSF for many years (1982-1996). She was also an affiliate scholar at the Center for Research on Women at Stanford University (1981-1988).
Cruikshank later taught courses on aging and women (1992 – 1997), in addition to gay and lesbian studies at CCSF, before moving to Maine in 1997. Cruikshank's introduction to working with older people came when she was did a graduate studies internship in gerontology at San Francisco State University, where she received an M.A. in gerontology in 1992.
Cruikshank has edited three major anthologies on lesbians: The Lesbian Path (1980, Angel Press; 1982, self-published; 1985, Grey Fox Press); Lesbian Studies, a women's history/lesbian studies text (1982, The Feminist Press) and New Lesbian Writing, a lesbian literature anthology (Grey Fox Press, 1984). In her papers, Cruikshank explains the three anthologies, their genesis and their inclusions. She traces their origins in the women's studies movement and through the lesbian academics' network created by the National Women's Studies Association (NWSA) and details the editorial process.
Cruikshank's correspondence and publications in the collection often discuss her experiences in teaching lesbian studies/women's studies and her life-long efforts to integrate lesbian and gay material into the college curriculum. Her correspondence in the collection also traces the networks of lesbian critics, academics and writers that were established through panels at the Modern Language Association's (MLA) and Gay Academic Union's (GAU) annual conventions, pioneering lesbian feminist periodicals of the 1970s, lesbian groups, women's studies programs, writing workshops, and women's publishing presses.
Cruikshank currently teaches women's studies at the University of Maine, where she is also affiliated with the Center on Aging (1997-present). She lives in a small fishing village on the eastern coast of Maine. Her most recent anthology, Fierce with Reality: an Anthology of Literature about Aging (1995, 2007) grew out of her master's thesis in gerontology at San Francisco State University. Her other books include Thomas Babington Macaulay (1978), The Gay and Lesbian Liberation Movement (1992), and Learning to be Old: Gender, Culture, and Aging (2003). She was recently awarded a Fulbright Fellowship to conduct seminars and lectures on women and aging at the University of Victoria Centre on Aging, in British Columbia, during the fall 2007 semester.
Chronology
1940 Born, Duluth, MN.
1962 Received a B.A. in English from St. Scholastica, Duluth, MN.
1969 Received a Ph.D. in Victorian literature from Loyola University in Chicago, IL; wrote dissertation on Thomas B. Macaulay.
1969 - 1970 Taught English at Loyala University in Chicago, IL.
1970 - 1972 Taught English at Central College in Pella, IA.
1974 Taught English at St. John's University in Collegeville, MN.
1975-1977 Started teaching English at Minnesota State University (MSU), Mankato; helped establish the first women's studies department at MSU, for which she served as director.
1977 In the Fall, moved to San Francisco, CA; worked as a resources director for a short-lived grassroots project, the Gay National Educational Switchboard.
1978 Published dissertation called Thomas Babington Macaulay as part of the Twayne English authors series.
1980 The Lesbian Path was first published by Angel Press in Monterey.
1980, Aug Became head of a small program in Continuing Education at the University of San Francisco (USF).
1980, Dec Got fired from teaching job at USF.
1981 Started teaching in the English department at City College of San Francisco (CCSF); taught English as a Second Language (ESL).
1981 - 1988 Served as an affiliate scholar at the Center for Research on Women at Stanford University.
1982 Self-published first work on a lesbian topic, Lesbian Path, a collection of autobiographical writings.
1982 Published Lesbian Studies, a women's history and lesbian studies text (The Feminist Press).
1982 - 1997 Appointed as first female faculty member to teach CCSF's gay and lesbian literature course; taught an introductory women's studies course and lesbian and gay literature at CCSF for many years.
1984 Published New Lesbian Writing, a lesbian literature anthology (Grey Fox Press).
1985 Lesbian Path published in a revised and expanded edition by Grey Fox Press.
1992 Received an M.A. in gerontology from San Francisco State University.
1997 - Present Moved to Maine and began teaching in the women's studies department at the University of Maine, Orono; also affiliated with the University of Maine Center on Aging.
2003 Published Learning to be Old: Gender, Culture and Aging.
2007 Published Fierce with Reality: an Anthology of Literature about Aging.
2007 Awarded Fullbright Fellowship to conduct seminars and lectures on women and aging at the University of Victoria Centre on Aging, in British Columbia during the fall 2007 semester.
Scope and Content
The Margaret Cruikshank collection is a mixture of professional and personal papers. Papers date from 1971-1986, with the majority spanning the period 1979-1986. Among the papers are manuscripts and notes for books, articles and reviews authored by Cruikshank; drafts and revisions with correspondence relating to the editorial process; publicity materials, notes by Cruikshank, printed matter, course syllabi and readings, bibliographies, photographs and personal correspondence.
Publications, 1977-1986, (Series 1, Boxes 1-10), include drafts of Cruikshank's published and unpublished papers and book reviews and manuscript drafts of three of her books: Lesbian path (1980, 1982, 1985), a collection of autobiographical writings; Lesbian Studies (1982), a women's history and lesbian studies text and New Lesbian Writing (1984), a lesbian literature anthology. Among Cruikshank's notes are revisions relating to the editorial process, names, addresses and phone numbers; mailing lists and list of readers and contributing authors. Publicity materials and correspondence relating to Cruikshank's books are also included here.
Research files and notes, 1971-1986, n.d., (Series 2, Box 11), consist of publicity materials from various lesbian, gay and women's publications, books/bookstores and organizations. This includes flyers, pamphlets and brochures; newspaper and magazine clippings; newsletters; bibliographies and related correspondence. Notes and conference proposals by Cruikshank for panels at the National Women's Studies Association (NWSA), Modern Language Association (MLA) and Gay Academic Union (GAU) annual conferences, proposed submissions for articles and book reviews by Cruikshank and calls for papers and requests to write and review are also included here. Also included are articles that mention Cruikshank that are not related to her publications.
Course syllabi and readings, 1982-1985 (Series 3, Box 11), relates to Introduction to Women's Studies and Lesbian Gay Literature courses taught by Cruikshank at the City College of San Francisco (CCSF) and includes course syllabi and readings, bibliographies, notes by Cruikshank and student papers.
Publications not authored by Cruikshank, 1979-1983, n.d., (Series 4, Box 11, 14), consists of drafts of published and unpublished papers, bibliographies and galley proofs.
Personal correspondence, 1971-1976, (Series 5, Boxes 12-13), consists of personal correspondence from Sue Ebbers to Cruikshank and several photos.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1. Publications, 1977-1986. Boxes 1-10
Series 2. Research files and notes, 1971-1986, n.d.. Box 11
Series 3. Course syllabi and readings, 1982-1985. Box 11
Series 4. Publications not authored by Cruikshank, 1979-1983, n.d.. Box 11, 14
Series 5. Personal correspondence, 1971-1976. Boxes 12-13
Related Material
This collection forms part of the The June L. Mazer Archive at UCLA.
Cruikshank, Margaret
- Publications, 1977-1986; Series 1.; Boxes 1-10
  Scope and Contents note
  Papers relate to three published works edited by Cruikshank: Lesbian Path, a collection of autobiographical writings (1980, Angel Press; 1982, self-published; 1985, Grey Fox Press); Lesbian Studies, a women's and lesbian studies text (1982, The Feminist Press); and New Lesbian Writing, a lesbian literature anthology (1984, Grey Fox Press). The files include correspondence, initial proposals, drafts with various reader comments, biographical sketches, notes by Cruikshank, published articles and papers by Cruikshank and other authors including those works which were considered but not included in the final publications of the books, and draft manuscripts.
  Arrangement note
  Alphabetical by contributing author or folder label. NOTE: in most cases, folder headings were assigned by Margaret Cruikshank.
  - Lesbian Studies, 1980-1981; Subseries 1.; Boxes 1-7
    Alphabetical by contributing author or folder label or chronological by date.
    Essays and reprints of articles from the three sections of Lesbian Studies, drafts with various reader comments, notes by Cruikshank and members of the readers committee, the completed manuscript of Lesbian Studies, and bibliographies, indexes and course syllabi from the appendix of resources. The first section concerns the lesbian professor/researcher experience in academia, and the second, aspects of teaching/exploring lesbian themes in the university classroom. The third section is essentially a series of bibliographic essays addressing various subject areas: black lesbians, history, biography, literature, older lesbians, science, physical education and sport, and love between women in prison. The third section is followed by an appendix, which provides useful resources, including bibliographies, indexes and syllabi. NOTE: Box 1 files include essays and reprints of articles which were included in the final publication of the book and Box 2 files include those essays and reprints of articles which were considered but not included in the final publication of the book.
    - Lesbian Studies Section One: Lesbians in Academia, 1980-1981; 5 folders (Box 1)
      Drafts and reprints of essays from the first section of Lesbian Studies entitled "Lesbians in the Academic World: The Personal/Political Experience" which concerns the lesbian professor/researcher experience in academia. Contributing authors include Paula Bennett, Doris Davenport, Toni A.H. McNaron, Mab Segrest and Sue Sturtz.
    - Lesbian Studies Section Two: Lesbians in the Classroom, 1980-1981; 9 folders (Box 1)
      Drafts and reprints of essays from the second section of Lesbian Studies entitled "In the Classroom" which concerns aspects of teaching/exploring lesbian themes in the university classroom. Contributing authors include Jane Gurko, Elly Bulkin, Barbara Smith, Cherrie Moraga, Nancy Manahan, Coralyn Fontaine, Evelyn Torton Beck, Toni A.H. McNaron, Madeline Davis and Clare Bright.
    - Lesbian Studies Section Three: New Research/New Perspectives, 1980-1981; 15 folders (Box 1)
      Drafts and reprints of essays from the third section of Lesbian Studies entitled "New Research/New Perspectives" addressing various subject areas: black lesbians, history, biography, literature, older lesbians, science, physical education and sport, and love between women in prison. Contributing authors include JR Roberts, Lynda Koolish, Estelle Freedman, Lillian Faderman, Frances Doughty, Bonnie Zimmerman, Kathy Hickok, Becky Birtha, Clare Potter, Ida VSW Red, Matile Poor, H. Patricia Hynes, Linn ni Cobhan, Karlene Faith and Marilyn Frye.
    - Submissions to Lesbian Studies, 1980-1981; 23 folders (Box 2)
      Essays and reprints of articles which were considered but not included in the final publication of Lesbian Studies. Authors include: Elly Bulkin; Cheryl Clarke; Anita Cornwell; Margaret Cruikshank; Rosemary Curb; P.M. Duffey-Igrassia; Joy Fisher; Jane Gurko; Barbara Hammer; Monika Kehoe; Noretta Koertge; J. Lee Lehman; Del Martin and Sally Gearhart; Toni McNaron; Moving Cloud (June Boyd); Marilyn Murphy; Barbara Noda; Arlene Raven; Patricia Reagan; Cynthia Rich; Julia Stanley; Susan Leigh Star; and Bonnie Zimmerman.
    - Completed manuscript (most recent draft) of Lesbian Studies, 1980-1981; 8 folders (Box 3)
      Completed manuscript with corrections includes introduction, essays and reprints of articles by Cruikshank and contributing authors, a Resources section, sample syllabi from courses on women's and lesbian studies, an extensive bibliography and Contributors' Notes.
      General note
      Manuscript includes two articles which were part of the book until the very end but not included in the final publication of the book: "Teaching the Lesbian Novel In and Out of Academia" by Joy Fisher and "The Lesbian Film Artist Births Herself: A Talk with Barbara Hammer" by Margaret Cruikshank.
    - Completed manuscript (earlier draft) of Lesbian Studies, 1980-1981; 8 folders (Box 4)
      Completed manuscript with corrections includes introduction, essays and reprints of articles by Cruikshank and contributing authors, a Resources section, sample syllabi from courses on women's and lesbian studies, an extensive bibliography and Contributors' Notes (see Box 3 for most recent draft of completed manuscript).
    - Lesbian Studies drafts, 1980-1981; 11 folders (Box 5, Folder 1 - 11)
      Drafts with various reader comments, notes by Cruikshank and members of the Readers Committee for Lesbian Studies and related correspondence and memoranda. This material includes notes on editorial changes. Readers for Lesbian Studies introduction include Clare Potter, Ida Red and Matile Poor. Readers Committee members include Nancy Manahan, Kathy Hickok, Jane Gurko, Bonnie Zimmerman, Sue Sturtz and Madeline Davis.
    - Correspondence Requests for submission. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Book reviews and publicity materials, 1981-1983; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 10)
      Contains book reviews and news notes, press clippings and ephemera relating to Lesbian Studies and lesbian and women's publishing.
      All newsprint materials were photocopied onto acid-free paper and oversized publications and clippings were removed and placed in oversized Box 14.
    - Business records for Lesbian Studies, 1980; 2 folders (Box 6, Folder 11 - 12)
      Expense records and original contract for Lesbian Studies.
    - Lesbian Studies original proposal, 1980-1981; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Research relating to Lesbian Studies Resources Section, 1981-1983; 6 folders (Box 6, Folder 4 - 9)
      Background/research files on educational and cultural work that lesbians were doing for the field of lesbian studies in the 1970s and early 1980s: archives, history projects and history slide shows; art, films, grants and dissertations; bibliographies; groups, centers and conferences; publishers, periodicals and special issues of periodicals; works in progress and unpublished works. Many of these are listed in the Resources Section of Lesbian Studies.
    - Research relating to Lesbian Studies Appendix, 1981-1983; 2 folders (Box 6, Folder 2 - 3)
      Background/research notes including course syllabi from university courses on lesbian studies and published and unpublished bibliographies of books and articles useful to the lesbian studies curriculum. Many of these are listed in the Appendix Section of Lesbian Studies.
    - Lesbian Studies correspondence, 1979-1982; 11 folders (Box 7, Folder 1 - 11)
      Requests for submissions to Lesbian Studies and correspondence between Cruikshank and contributors to Lesbian Studies and the Feminist Press, the publisher of Lesbian Studies. Cruikshank maintained a steady correspondence with many lesbian academics, writers, artists, teachers and activists, many of whom were published in her anthologies. The most notable of these include Madeline Davis, Jane Rule, Rosemary Curb, Nancy Manahan and Bonnie Zimmerman. This material also includes Cruikshank's correspondence with various lesbian, gay and women's studies publications and organizations, women's studies programs, writing workshops, and women's publishing presses.
  - Lesbian Path, 1980-1982; Subseries 2.; Box 9, 14
    Alphabetical by folder label.
    The completed manuscript of Lesbian Path, a collection of autobiographical writings from lesbians' lives edited by Cruikshank, correspondence, and publicity announcements and reviews. The Lesbian Path, Cruikshank's first published work on a lesbian topic, consists of personal narratives written by lesbians: some quite celebrated as writers, musicians, teachers and activists; many unknown before the publication of their stories. Initially published by Angel Press in 1980, then self-published by Cruikshank in 1982, The Lesbian Path was expanded and reprinted in 1985 by Grey Fox Press.
    - Book reviews and publicity materials for Lesbian Path, 1980-1981; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 6)
      Contains book reviews and news notes, press clippings and ephemera relating to Lesbian Path.
    - Completed manuscript of Lesbian Path, 1980-1981; 3 folders (Box 9, Folder 1 - 3)
      Working title was Labyris
    - Correspondence relating to Lesbian Path, 1981-1982; 2 folders (Box 9, Folder 9 - 10)
      Correspondence between Cruikshank and contributors to Lesbian Path and Carrier Pigeon/Alyson Publications, the publisher of the second reprinted edition (1985) of Lesbian Path.
      Of particular interest is the correspondence between Cruikshank and Barbara Gittings and the file of clippings and correspondence relating to the anti-semitism criticism of Lesbian Path by Selma Miriam in Sinister Wisdom.
    - Lesbian Path galleys, 1980-1981; 2 folders (Box 9, Folder 4 - 5)
    - Motheroot Journal: A Women's Review of the Small Presses, 1980; Vol. 2 no. 2 (Summer 1980) (Box 14)
      Includes autobiographical essay by Cruikshank relating to Lesbian Path and book review of Lesbian Path.
      See Box 9 for other book reviews and publicity materials for Lesbian Path.
    - Correspondence RE: anti-Semitism criticism in Sinister Wisdom by Selma Miriam (Box 9, Folder 7 - 8)
  - New Lesbian Writing, 1982-1984; Subseries 3.; Boxes 9-10, 14
    The completed manuscript of New Lesbian Writing, a lesbian literature anthology edited by Cruikshank and published by Grey Fox Press in 1984, correspondence, publicity announcements, reviews and submissions which were considered but not included in the final publication of the book. The book contains poetry, autobiographical excerpts by a number of women (including four who are over 65 years of age), short fiction and essays. The book also includes an extensive bibliography of lesbian literature from 1980 to 1983.
    - Completed manuscript of New Lesbian Writing, 1984; 3 folders (Box 9, Folder 11 - 13)
      Manuscript goes from Pg 83 to 90 but Pgs 84-89 are not missing pages.
    - New Lesbian Writing correspondence and notes, 1981-1983; 6 folders (Box 10, Folder 1 - 6)
      Includes correspondence relating to copyright/contract dispute with Karla Jay "Prince Charming"
    - New Lesbian Writing publicity announcements, press releases and book reviews, 1984; 2 folders (Box 10, Folder 11 - 12)
      See Box 14 for oversized periodical book reviews relating to New Lesbian Writing.
    - New Lesbian Writing signed contracts, 1983; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 7)
      Signed contracts between Cruikshank and contributors to New Lesbian Writing
    - Submissions to New Lesbian Writing, 1984; 3 folders (Box 10, Folder 8 - 10)
      Folders 1 and 2 include those submissions which were included in the final publication of New Lesbian Writing. Folder 3 includes those submissions which were not included in the final publication of the book.
    - Gay Community News, 1984, Sept.; 2 issues (Box 14)
      Includes interview with Cruikshank and book review of New Lesbian Writing.